宮口航平 (Kohei MIYAGUCHI), Ph.D.

☑ koheimiyaguchi@gmail.com

in koheim

https://koheimiya.github.io/



Highlights

Published and presented a number of research papers at top-tier international conferences of machine learning (ML) and artificial intelligence (AI). Led or played key roles in various projects of ML/AI applications through developing AI-based products and engaging in collaborative research with clients. Experience in mentoring interns and students. Specialized in learning theory and reinforcement learning.

Employment History

2024 - NOW

Chief Researcher, LY Research.

2019 - 2024

Staff Research Scientist, IBM Research – Tokyo.

Education

2016 - 2019

Ph.D., The University of Tokyo, Grad. School of Information Science and Technology. Thesis: *Learning High-dimensional Models with the Minimum Description Length Principle*.

Data Scientist, The University of Tokyo, Data Science School.

2014 - 2016

M.Sc. Eng., The University of Tokyo, Grad. School of Information Science and Technology.

Thesis: Study on Learning from Nonstationary Time Series.

2012 - 2014

B.Sc. Eng., The University of Tokyo, Dept. of Mathematical Engineering and Information Physics.

Research Publications

Conference Proceedings (Peer Reviewed)

- **K. Miyaguchi**, "Worst-case offline reinforcement learning with arbitrary data support," in *The Thirty-eighth Annual Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems*, 2024. **©** URL: https://openreview.net/forum?id=63VajkIDEu.
- H. Kajino, **K. Miyaguchi**, and T. Osogami, "Biases in evaluation of molecular optimization methods and bias reduction strategies," in *International Conference on Machine Learning, ICML 2023, 23-29 July 2023, Honolulu, Hawaii, USA*, A. Krause, E. Brunskill, K. Cho, B. Engelhardt, S. Sabato, and J. Scarlett, Eds., ser. Proceedings of Machine Learning Research, vol. 202, PMLR, 2023, pp. 15 567–15 585. **9** URL: https://proceedings.mlr.press/v202/kajino23a.html.
- T. Katsuki, **K. Miyaguchi**, A. Koseki, T. Iwamori, R. Yanagiya, and A. Suzuki, "Cumulative stay-time representation for electronic health records in medical event time prediction," in *Proceedings of the Thirty-First International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence, IJCAI 2022, Vienna, Austria, 23-29 July 2022, L. D. Raedt, Ed., ijcai.org, 2022, pp. 3861–3867. ODOI: 10.24963/IJCAI.2022/536.*
- M. Kobayashi, **K. Miyaguchi**, and S. Matsushima, "Detection of unobserved common cause in discrete data based on the MDL principle," in *IEEE International Conference on Big Data, Big Data 2022, Osaka, Japan, December 17-20, 2022*, S. Tsumoto et al., Eds., IEEE, 2022, pp. 45–54. **9** DOI: 10.1109/BIGDATA55660.2022.10020351.

- K. Miyaguchi, "A theoretical framework of almost hyperparameter-free hyperparameter selection methods for offline policy evaluation," in Workshop on AI for Decision Optimization, The Thirty-Sixth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, AAAI 2022, Vancouver, BC, Canada, Feburary 28 March 1, 2022, vol. abs/2201.02300, 2022. arXiv: 2201.02300. © URL: https://research.ibm.com/haifa/Workshops/AAAI-22-AI4DO/.
- **K. Miyaguchi**, T. Katsuki, A. Koseki, and T. Iwamori, "Variational inference for discriminative learning with generative modeling of feature incompletion," in *The Tenth International Conference on Learning Representations, ICLR 2022, Virtual Event, April 25-29, 2022*, OpenReview.net, 2022. **9** URL: https://openreview.net/forum?id=qnQN4yr6FJz.
- H. Yanagisawa, K. Miyaguchi, and T. Katsuki, "Hierarchical lattice layer for partially monotone neural networks," in Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 35: Annual Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems 2022, New Orleans, LA, USA, November 28 December 9, 2022, S. Koyejo, S. Mohamed, A. Agarwal, D. Belgrave, K. Cho, and A. Oh, Eds., 2022. © URL: http://papers.nips.cc/paper%5C_files/paper/2022/hash/47ed62021460f2e9bba7be3e74260090-Abstract-Conference.html.
- K. Miyaguchi, "Asymptotically exact error characterization of offline policy evaluation with misspecified linear models," in Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 34: Annual Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems 2021, NeurIPS 2021, December 6-14, 2021, virtual, M. Ranzato, A. Beygelzimer, Y. N. Dauphin, P. Liang, and J. W. Vaughan, Eds., 2021, pp. 28573-28584. © URL: https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper/2021/hash/f0282b5ff85e7c9c66200d780bd7e72e-Abstract.html.
- **K. Miyaguchi** and H. Kajino, "Cogra: Concept-drift-aware stochastic gradient descent for time-series forecasting," in *The Thirty-Third AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, AAAI 2019, The Thirty-First Innovative Applications of Artificial Intelligence Conference, IAAI 2019, The Ninth AAAI Symposium on Educational Advances in Artificial Intelligence, EAAI 2019, Honolulu, Hawaii, USA, January 27 February 1, 2019, AAAI Press, 2019, pp. 4594–4601. ODI: 10.1609/AAAI.V33I01.33014594.*
- K. Miyaguchi and K. Yamanishi, "Adaptive minimax regret against smooth logarithmic losses over high-dimensional l1-balls via envelope complexity," in *The 22nd International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics, AISTATS 2019, 16-18 April 2019, Naha, Okinawa, Japan,* K. Chaudhuri and M. Sugiyama, Eds., ser. Proceedings of Machine Learning Research, vol. 89, PMLR, 2019, pp. 3440–3448.

 OURL: http://proceedings.mlr.press/v89/miyaguchi19a.html.
- R. Kaneko, **K. Miyaguchi**, and K. Yamanishi, "Detecting changes in streaming data with information-theoretic windowing," in 2017 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (IEEE BigData 2017), Boston, MA, USA, December 11-14, 2017, J. Nie et al., Eds., IEEE Computer Society, 2017, pp. 646–655. ODI: 10.1109/BIGDATA.2017.8257980.
- K. Miyaguchi, S. Matsushima, and K. Yamanishi, "Sparse graphical modeling via stochastic complexity," in *Proceedings of the 2017 SIAM International Conference on Data Mining, Houston, Texas, USA, April 27-29, 2017,* N. V. Chawla and W. Wang, Eds., SIAM, 2017, pp. 723–731. ODI: 10.1137/1.9781611974973.81.
- A. Suzuki, **K. Miyaguchi**, and K. Yamanishi, "Structure selection for convolutive non-negative matrix factorization using normalized maximum likelihood coding," in *IEEE 16th International Conference on Data Mining, ICDM 2016, December 12-15, 2016, Barcelona, Spain*, F. Bonchi, J. Domingo-Ferrer, R. Baeza-Yates, Z. Zhou, and X. Wu, Eds., IEEE Computer Society, 2016, pp. 1221–1226. DOI: 10.1109/ICDM.2016.0163.
- K. Yamanishi and K. Miyaguchi, "Detecting gradual changes from data stream using mdl-change statistics," in 2016 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (IEEE BigData 2016), Washington DC, USA, December 5-8, 2016, J. Joshi et al., Eds., IEEE Computer Society, 2016, pp. 156–163. ODOI: 10.1109/BIGDATA.2016.7840601.

K. Miyaguchi and K. Yamanishi, "On-line detection of continuous changes in stochastic processes," in 2015 IEEE International Conference on Data Science and Advanced Analytics, DSAA 2015, Campus des Cordeliers, Paris, France, October 19-21, 2015, IEEE, 2015, pp. 1-9. ODI: 10.1109/DSAA.2015.7344783.

Journal Articles (Peer Reviewed)

- **K. Miyaguchi** and K. Yamanishi, "High-dimensional penalty selection via minimum description length principle," *Mach. Learn.*, vol. 107, no. 8-10, pp. 1283–1302, 2018. DOI: 10.1007/S10994-018-5732-2.
- **K. Miyaguchi** and K. Yamanishi, "Online detection of continuous changes in stochastic processes," *Int. J. Data Sci. Anal.*, vol. 3, no. 3, pp. 213–229, 2017. **Ø** DOI: 10.1007/S41060-017-0045-2.

Books and Chapters

H. Kajino, **K. Miyaguchi**, T. Osogami, R. Iwaki, and A. Wachi, *From reinforcement learning to reliable decision making (Japanese)*, K. Yamanishi, Ed. Saiensu-sha, 2024.

Experience

Invited Talk

- On Sufficient Conditions of Reinforcement Learning with Restricted Data, CIGS Interdisciplinary Symposium on Economics and Society 2024.
- Introduction to Statistical Learning Theory from Generalization Error Analysis,
 The 25th Information-Based Induction Sciences (IBIS) Workshop, Tutorial Session.
 - NeurIPS2021 Review on Deep Learning Theories, The 83rd JSAI Seminar.
- 2020 PAC-Bayesian Transportation Bound, RIKEN AIP Mathematical Seminar.

Awards and Achievements

- Best Presentation Award, The 23rd Information-Based Induction Sciences (IBIS) Workshop.
- **Student Award**, The fifth conference of The Japanese Society for Artificial Intelligence (JSAI).

Fellowship

- 2017 2019 Research Fellowship for Young Scientist (DC2), Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS).
- 2016 2017 Research Assistant, Grad. School of Information Science and Technology, The University of Tokyo.

Academic Service

- 2024 NOW Program Committee Member, The Information-Based Induction Sciences and Machine Learning (IBISML).
- 2019 2020 **Program Committee Member**, JSAI.

Skills

Languages English (business level), Japanese (native).

Coding Python, C/C++, LaTeX,

References

Available on Request